<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Folklore Database</title>
    <link>https://kimbe.github.io/folklore-database/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Folklore Database</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://kimbe.github.io/folklore-database/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hungry Grass on the Nephin Road</title>
      <link>https://kimbe.github.io/folklore-database/map/hungry-grass-mayo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kimbe.github.io/folklore-database/map/hungry-grass-mayo/</guid>
      <description>The &amp;ldquo;hungry grass&amp;rdquo; (fear gortach) is said to grow where someone died of famine. Anyone who steps on it is struck by sudden weakness and hunger until they eat.
On the old road near Nephin, a particular patch was marked by a small cairn so travellers could avoid it. The tradition was still recalled by older residents in the mid-twentieth century.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>St Brigid&#39;s Well, Kildare</title>
      <link>https://kimbe.github.io/folklore-database/map/st-brigid-kildare/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kimbe.github.io/folklore-database/map/st-brigid-kildare/</guid>
      <description>St Brigid&amp;rsquo;s Well at Kildare has been a focus of devotion and rounds (turás) for centuries. Pilgrims perform a set number of circuits and recite prayers; the water is used for blessing and cure.
The site is associated with the saint&amp;rsquo;s monastery and the perpetual fire. Rounds are especially common on 1 February (St Brigid&amp;rsquo;s Day) and during the summer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Banshee of Killarney</title>
      <link>https://kimbe.github.io/folklore-database/map/banshee-killarney/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kimbe.github.io/folklore-database/map/banshee-killarney/</guid>
      <description>The banshee is said to wail from the old oak woods near the lakes when a death is imminent in certain families. She is described as a tall woman in grey, combing her long hair.
Several accounts from the nineteenth century agree that the cry was heard before the passing of members of the O&amp;rsquo;Donoghue and related families. One witness reported hearing it three nights in a row before his uncle&amp;rsquo;s death.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Fairy Fort at Ballincollig</title>
      <link>https://kimbe.github.io/folklore-database/map/fairy-fort-cork/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kimbe.github.io/folklore-database/map/fairy-fort-cork/</guid>
      <description>A ringfort (rath) near Ballincollig is traditionally avoided after dark. Locals say the fairies still use it, and that cutting the whitethorn around it brings bad luck.
Stories tell of a man who took a shortcut through the fort and lost his way for hours, though the distance was short. Another account describes lights seen moving inside the ring at night.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Headless Coach of Howth</title>
      <link>https://kimbe.github.io/folklore-database/map/headless-coach-dublin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kimbe.github.io/folklore-database/map/headless-coach-dublin/</guid>
      <description>A headless coach is said to drive along the road to Howth at night, drawn by black horses. Those who see it are warned of a death in the family. The coach is sometimes linked to the St Lawrence family or to an unspecified nobleman who broke a promise.
Sightings were still reported in the early twentieth century, especially around the bend near the summit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Púca of Glenmalure</title>
      <link>https://kimbe.github.io/folklore-database/map/puca-wicklow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kimbe.github.io/folklore-database/map/puca-wicklow/</guid>
      <description>The Púca of Glenmalure is said to appear as a black goat or a dark horse and lead night-time travellers astray. It is not always malevolent: in one tale it helps a lost man find his way after he speaks to it respectfully.
The glen&amp;rsquo;s isolation and history of rebellion have reinforced local belief in a &amp;ldquo;guardian&amp;rdquo; spirit of the place.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Selkie of Tory Island</title>
      <link>https://kimbe.github.io/folklore-database/map/selkie-donegal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kimbe.github.io/folklore-database/map/selkie-donegal/</guid>
      <description>Selkies—seals who shed their skins to become human—are part of Tory&amp;rsquo;s lore. Stories tell of fishermen who hid a selkie&amp;rsquo;s skin so she could not return to the sea and married her; when she found the skin years later, she left.
Other accounts describe selkies guiding boats through fog or warning of storms. The island&amp;rsquo;s dependence on the sea is reflected in these tales.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Will-o&#39;-the-Wisp in the Bog of Cloon</title>
      <link>https://kimbe.github.io/folklore-database/map/will-o-wisp-galway/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kimbe.github.io/folklore-database/map/will-o-wisp-galway/</guid>
      <description>Flickering lights over the bog near Cloon were explained as the &amp;ldquo;will-o&amp;rsquo;-the-wisp&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;ignis fatuus&amp;rdquo;, said to lead travellers into the soft ground. Older people warned children not to follow the lights.
Modern accounts sometimes attribute the phenomenon to marsh gas (methane), but the folk explanation persists in local memory.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
